Today's lecture will focus on agentic
evaluations and long horizon tasks. How
many of you have had to run an
evaluation for your project um to do
whatever you've been doing?
No one is running an evaluation. How are
you guys doing any projects?
Uh what evaluation tasks have you used
for agentic evaluations?
I'm going to call people out if I don't
get answers.
What do you What have you been using in
your project?
>> Like I wonder for like enacting
meditation. Do you mean like it has to
be something like speed bench or like
knowledge task? A multihoff knowledge
task.
>> All of those count, right?
>> Okay. Yeah. So then I guess like hard QA
QA. Okay. So that's a multihop question
answering task. Sweeten would also
count.
>> What else have you folks been using?
>> There's no other answers.
>> What about you?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, I'm a [clears throat]
I'm working on a private wiki for my
employer and I guess that down and make
notes out of that and then feed that
into a coding agent.
>> Okay, nice. Okay, so private wiki
question answers. So I think a lot of
this lecture will focus on what is
challenging about agentic evaluations
relative to where things have been
before and how things become harder. Um
the papers that we'll cover to cover
this topic will be uh focused on
measuring the ability of these models to
complete long tasks uh in terms of
what's the length of the task length as
in time horizon of the task that the
models can uh complete. uh also in terms
a second paper that we'll look at is GDP
val which was a recent benchmark that
was released by open AI. This will focus
on how do the models perform on real
world economically valuable tasks. So
there has been a lot of discussion
around uh the models can uh do tasks
that real world uh professionals can do.
So this is measuring that in a very real
sense. And then the last task will very
much focus on deep research style tasks.
So it is called deep scholar bench.
that's out of Stanford and it's a live
benchmark that focused on generative
research synthesis. So it takes a bunch
of papers and then tries to write the
related work section a task that I have
always wanted the language models to go
do for uh the papers that I write. So uh
this actually measures how good of a job
does the model do in in solving these
kind of tasks.
So one of the challenges of measuring
intelligence or progress of AI is that
we have to measure um what matters like
how is the how is the how are the models
progressing. So when we started about
four or five years ago even the fact
that the models could generate any
explanations was uh such a big deal and
now uh we may measure the progress of AI
in terms of whether we can uh forecast
how it will influence economics or how
it will influence safety. traditional
benchmarks uh which involve chat bots or
which involve say question answering or
singleshot just answering uh something
that was already in the context are
starting to saturate it fairly quickly.
However, we do need to measure uh both
in terms of capability and economic um
uh impact how these models are
progressing so that we can see what
their uh impact will be in the coming
years.
So in terms of um measuring capability
uh what we covered today is we are
looking at the task of how long or how
complex of a task can these models
accomplish. Um and the second question
we ask is what is the economic value of
the task that these uh models can do or
can they do real world tasks that humans
can currently do and the two papers that
we are uh referencing here is or the two
metrics that we are referencing here is
that MER refers to the time horizon
metric uh calibrated by uh human
professionals and GDP val compares uh
the win rate of model performing a task
uh relative to experts. So both of them
are equally valid metrics in certain
ways. Uh and the insights are very
similar but the trends that they measure
in terms of how models perform are quite
different.
So let's start with the first one.
So when you when you're talking to a
chatbot if you were talking to a chatbot
say 3 four five years ago
usually after a first couple of rounds
in multi-turn conversation the model
will be lost. it doesn't keep context of
what you were talking to it about. Today
as you talk to these models the
conversation can go pretty long. So it
does keep that context and that relates
then to the question of what is the
duration of the task that the model can
complete. So that's just the duration
question. And then the second question
is what's the percentage success? Can it
do do so reliably? So, METR this uh
particular benchmark um focuses on
duration of the task that model can
complete and then it associates a
reliability metric of like uh will it
complete it with 50% success or will it
complete it with 80% success and and so
on.
Um and the the universal anchor for um
these tasks ends up being the how much
time will it take humans to complete if
they were um professionals in in solving
these tasks.
So there is three task suites that are
used to design um this particular
benchmark.
One is extremely small. So 1 to 30
seconds. It basically focusing on just
atomic actions. So in software
engineering can you open a file? Can you
do something small?
The second one is edgecast which focuses
on more um 1 minute to 30 hours style of
task which is basically talking about
different software and research
engineering tasks. And then finally
rebench that's actually giving a full ML
research style tasks which can go on as
long as eight hours. So you've seen like
AI scientist paper covered in this graph
before. So uh similar style of
benchmarks. In total it covers about 170
tasks um going all the way from say 1
seconds to 8 hours. So if you were to
look at this um in terms of a division
you will see that edgecast has about 97
task. the the these are the one minute
to 30 hour tasks. SWAA has about 66
tasks and then rebench which are more
researching tasks that took take much
longer are about seven tasks. So the
first they do is they they collect these
tasks they vet the set of tasks that go
into each of these uh benchmark suites.
Then they actually have uh time
estimates from both human doing the task
and then the agent doing the task. From
human runs, they actually estimate the
amount of time it takes the human to
complete that task and whether they
found it difficult or not. And then for
the agent, uh they're measuring whether
they completed it reliably or not. And
uh finally based on enough data points,
they fit a curve which measures the
success rate versus the time estimate.
And based on that, they find the time
horizon for these models completing the
tasks. Um so that that gives a sense of
the horizon length relative to model
release dates. So what we'll see in
terms of trends are um for models
released on different dates uh roughly
what is the time horizon with which the
models complete the tasks 50% of the
time or 80% of the time uh 80% of the
time questions.
What is a task that takes you guys um a
couple of minutes and what's a task that
takes you guys say a couple of hours
that you think the like you would like
to delegate to the models
of
>> yes that that usually would take several
hours
so that that would be a great task and I
would fall somewhere in a cast or reb
task. Um any other takers related to
what you do?
>> Yeah.
>> I for each like reference
>> say that
>> double check the tag for each.
>> Okay. So in the paper writing you want
the the bip item to be correct. So you
wanted to go query the right websites
and find the bipe item.
>> Okay. How many minutes do you think that
was should take? So it falls more in
that one the edgecast style like diverse
tasks. Okay,
cool.
Any other task that people think that
the model should be like good at?
>> Okay.
>> Mhm.
would be able to faster.
>> So refactoring for code can be large or
can be small, right?
>> Yeah. Depends on
>> what the refactor requires. If the logic
stays the same as just moving around
code, then that perhaps a few hours can
be couple of days. Someone has to check
correctness of that as well. Makes
sense. So that one will fall perhaps
like closer to our bench. One can
imagine that there will be a version of
just like the coding related tasks.
Cool.
Okay,
it's okay. I ask a question about this
patient. So for the second step with the
for
task for this task human
people do it faster, some people do it
slower. Mhm.
>> So I'm just uh wondering so on one on
one case you just have one main
evaluator and then you have just one
result
on the other extreme you have like 100
you have distribution and you can
compare. So where is the head? So I'm
just curious where that's most of the
process.
>> So typically what's done with most of
the I mean getting a lot of experts to
solve the task is is uh relatively
expensive. So typically you will have a
few experts solve the task and then you
look for interrator agreement or
interhuman agreement in this particular
case and what you're saying is that
generally if the numbers are very far
off then you go get more data points and
if there is like generally agreement
then you kind of move on.
So just the example of tasks just
related to what the class talked about
where you wanted the literature review
section or you wanted the bipek um uh
being uh accurately classified or or or
the refactoring of the codebase. Some of
the example tasks of different durations
that were in this paper are like find a
shell script. So that that's perhaps
just take 3 seconds or Wikipedia
research. This is closer to the research
section that um that you wanted or
another one is like detect and fix a bug
in the input files for a simulation. So
that that takes like 10 minutes for a
human. Uh then there is like munching of
data. So data munching task where you're
transforming some JSON data from one
format to another. And then uh CUDA back
testing tool uh which basically you are
uh implementing custom CUDA kernels can
take uh tens of hours. So here it's like
8 hours and they're um aiming for a
certain performance improvement. So all
of these tests are part of um this
particular benchmark
and the way this actually addresses the
question you were asking. The way they
are going about um getting the human
baseline for task completion is that
they go and uh get uh skilled
professionals uh with roughly five years
of experience in the field to record
their completion times for successful
attempts and then they take a geometric
mean for the task difficulty rating
based on the humans that went and solved
this. One challenge with this is that
people who are experienced in the field
are conditioned to like what it means to
be successful in this. So they will
often underestimate the difficulty of
the task which might not correlate to
how the model sees whether this task is
difficult or not.
So in terms of trends what they found is
on the x-axis we have the human time to
complete and on the y-axis we have the
success rate going all the way from 0 to
uh one. So the model success rate um for
uh if you look at smaller tasks like the
1 to 30 secondond tasks which are the uh
swaa tasks all the green tasks that's
generally on the higher side for
edgecast tasks which are basically the
tasks which are diverse task going all
the way from say few minutes to uh
several hours that's all over the place
so it's anywhere from uh8 being the
highest all the way to zero and then the
re bench tasks have some success but
like tend to be on the lower side at
this point in time. Um there have been
uh papers saying that they are making
progress on rebench tasks but generally
it's a much harder task uh in terms of
like uh the human time to complete. It
takes long and then the model success
rate is also fairly low. So the longer
the task the harder it's for models to
stay on track and complete and this is
partly why agentic evaluations and what
you measure um starts to become a
challenging aspect.
In terms of trends, if you were to uh we
we chatted about the fact that if you
were to query these models about 2019
when GBT2 came out, uh typically the
models would really just address tasks
that were 2 seconds long. So on the
y-axis you have the task time for
completion with 50% success rate. So it
doesn't have to be completely reliable.
Uh so in 2019 when um GP2 came out only
2 seconds uh closer to GBD4 which is
2023 uh you are starting to see few
minutes and uh when we have claw 3.7 and
oven at that point you're starting to
see a few hours. Now note that this is
almost like a doubling because this is
um so it's it's doubling every 7 months.
But the other thing to note here is that
even though these tasks are being
completed, the reliability is not high.
They are only being completed 50% of the
time. So that's like saying that you
gave your task to an intern, but it only
completes it 50% of the time. So it
might come back with an answer or it
might might not. So there's always some
amount of uncertainty.
[snorts]
So uh this is just making the same point
that going from BGPD2 which was just 2
seconds to GPD4 which was like 8
minutes. Now cloud 3.7 sonnet in 2025
can go all the way to 59 minutes with
50% success rate. And what is really
driving this improvement? So some of the
capabilities that we are seeing in the
model that are really helpful in terms
of driving these improvements are better
logical reasoning. So the models can um
we've covered a lot of previous lectures
on the models learn how to reason
better. So the reasoning capabilities
definitely drive some of these
improvements. Uh code generation
capabilities have improved. So you uh we
have covered several lectures where
you've seen the models do better on the
code generation side. So that's
definitely driving some of these
improvements. Uh tool use. So we covered
React and several papers around just how
the models use tools. So that also has
added up. And then in general uh there
has been a focus on getting these models
to be more reliable so that they're not
repetitive in just repeating the same
behavior over and over again. And
finally you want these models to
generally recover from errors. I mean if
you're going to do an 8-hour task you're
going to have some steps which are going
to be wrong. So you have to recover from
those errors and you need a better
awareness of what is your final goal and
some notion of state of or memory of um
what is the final goal and how far along
are you in make terms of making progress
towards that goal. Um other aspects of
what folks have seen is driving these
improvements. Any comments?
Why do you think cloud code does better
today relative to say last year?
How many people use code or codex?
>> I think there's new trend for context
engineering. People are just learning
how to structure the context better so
that the tooling just becomes better and
improves the improve make the
improvements.
>> So what you're saying is I'm just
repeating for the class that context
engineering or being able to structure
the context better over multiple time
steps is is starting to improve which
also helps.
>> Thank you. you see like compaction
window that happens when blog basically
gets to the end of its um context.
>> Yes.
>> I think just like maybe from feedback of
actual people using it and then like I I
I know that for cursor they have this
like online RL thing right for tab
combinations. So I wonder maybe I don't
know for how that works with with board
for cloud code but I guess supposedly
they get some sort of feedback that from
the user logs and then try to either
back back probably or just kind of
figuratively in the workflow that
>> so you address the classic problems that
are starting to show up. Um
>> yes.
>> So when the problems the um is like very
compact nowaday
so when when problems are really complex
nowadays the coding agents um you can
trigger like explicit ping stuff. And so
that kind of helps them like when
problems are really hard and so just
stick to the planning and this kind of
reduces some trial and errors with fixed
plan.
>> Nice. So what he's saying is that if you
look at when the problem is very complex
the model as a first step does some
planning. So it breaks down the problem
into multiple steps and often times when
it uh goes and executes some of the
steps it might actually trigger
replanning. So it might actually come up
with a new set of steps to go do uh
based on the data it's collected.
That's very good insight.
>> So when you use cross code sometimes the
code has error. Mhm.
>> I mean the code is the code doesn't have
problem. So user but user may include
the code and then the code will know
that code has
>> so that mean that receiving the two user
>> yes so there's always the user feedback
where the user says what you give me is
is not right so then [snorts]
the model has to redo the job
>> that's same as doing like someone has
given you an assignment And then if it's
not to the satisfaction, you got to
redo, right? Uh, okay, that's fair. How
does memory play out in all of this or
context? What's in context?
We covered like we had a whole lecture
on memory.
>> Why is memory important?
>> Okay. So sometimes the agents have like
atomic memory nominal
code base. So like that's kind of like
sampling from the updating the partner
so it knows better like what the
environment looks like.
>> Okay. So what is saying is that uh
sometimes the agent might actually uh
need to understand what the environment
is better. So for example an
understanding of the code bases. So
having memory helps uh keep that
understanding of if it's going to
operate over similar codebase. Um okay
thank you.
[snorts] Okay let's keep going. So now
let's take a look at reliability aspect
of it. So capability is only one u axis
along which we want these models to do
better. Reliability is the other one. So
what we are measuring here is again
x-axis is the model release date and now
we want to see how the models do at 80%
success rate. So the gray line is the
50% uh reliability one and then the blue
line is the 80% success rate um and
y-axis is uh the time taken by the
models to complete u the tasks. So what
you see here is that while we were
claiming that you can get all the way up
to 59 minutes in 2025 with the latest
and greatest models, uh if you want high
reliability, you are still at a few
minutes or or uh maybe tens of minutes.
And uh so to get 80% success rate with
the models, there's a big delta between
the 59 minutes that we were claiming
claiming with the best [snorts] model
versus uh at 80% success rate, you're
still closer to say somewhere around
8 to 10 minutes. So, so that that's big
delta roughly tells you that there's a
lot of headroom to make in terms of
reliability so that the model comes back
and is successful most of the time.
>> Yes.
>> So, do you [clears throat] believe this
based on your experience?
>> Let's ask that question at the end of
the lecture because you will have a lot
more. I mean the whole lecture is about
this.
Oh, just wondering what paper is this
brought from.
>> This is from the paper. Paper is posted
online.
>> Oh, the the first paper.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I the both the paper and the
slides are online right now.
>> So, basically uh 80% horizon is uh basic
uh is still showing doubling time uh
similar uh time horizons uh but it is
saying that you have uh five five it's
five weeks shorter. So the 15 minutes is
what cloud 3.7 can achieve 80% of the
time versus 59 minutes uh 50% of the
time. So this gap basically says that if
you're trying to deploy these uh models
in real world tasks then this is um
there will be reliability challenges
even for moderately complex tasks. So
that requires bu there's definitely a
lot of headroom in how we build systems
on top of these models.
And an important question to ask is what
are the kind of failures that we uh run
into with these models and this is uh
looking at both GPD4 which is a
non-reasoning model and 01 which is a
reasoning model. Now this paper is a bit
older and you can like refer to things
that are a bit newer but at the same
time the kind of failure modes are very
similar in in many cases. So we can take
a look here. So the kind of failure
modes that they found are closer to uh
either poor planning. So the model
doesn't know how to break the task it
was given down into steps. Um poor tool
choice so that the set of tools that it
tries to choose here uh may or may not
be correct and and there were errors
along both these axes in the uh GBD4 and
01. Um a second failure type is
incorrect mental math or reasoning style
task. So here the model is basically
doing some sort of math or reasoning but
it's doing it incorrectly.
Another failure type is that prematurely
it abandons the tasks because it goes
around some repetitive behavior but is
not quite able to figure out what it
means for the task to be successful. Um
another failure mode uh is that the the
model will basically get into a
repetitive loop. So it will basically go
do some actions and then um that's still
the highest probability action even
after it has failed. So it then goes and
does that action again. Um so it might
basically be with high probability
repeating the same action. So with GBD4
this was uh pretty high for for O1 this
has u become lower and then there's
other category of tasks that they showed
um there are other categories of
failures that they showed are also
prevalent but this gives you a sense of
like planning tool choice um reasoning
errors um not being able to figure out
when to when the task is completed and
then just repetitive loops tend to be
some of the failure modes for these
models and failure mode analysis is very
useful in understanding where the models
can or cannot improve.
>> Okay.
>> Is this a common
typically
different categories or
>> Yes. Okay. So that you like
>> not similar categories but it's common
to evaluate the models and then if
you're saying that you have a
challenging benchmark then you would
showcase where do the models fail what
is the common failure pattern
>> and the thing is human
>> human or or self-inflicted pain.
So you go evaluate the model yourself
and see where it's failing. I think we
have been asking you guys to do that for
homeworks where you go actually try to
do the selfative refinement then you
have to evaluate where the model failed.
Okay. So uh some of the some of the
challenges in uh this benchmark so like
the so no benchmark is ever perfect. U
every benchmark has some challenges. So
some of the things um that METR did get
right is that it's a first attempt at
measuring what is the time horizon of
tasks that these models can complete and
some of the challenges u that the model
does um does not quite solve is that it
has lower performance on tasks that are
messy like where there's not one single
correct answer or there's some amount of
complexity involved. uh but if you have
some amount of messiness then um like
similar trends will be there at in
different categories of tasks. Another
one is that if you try to do a look at
SWE um
SWEBench similar has a similar trend to
what we were showing in in in the all
the plots before but um the annotators
generally underestimate SWEBench and the
models also have seen most of the GitHub
repositories. So a lot of the um
estimates that are made on swbanch tend
to be shorter in terms of doubling time
relative to if if it was in completely
unseen repository.
A third uh challenge with the with the
benchmark is that if you actually have
internal uh pull requests. So this is
for like internal code bases. Then what
has been found is that if you put
contractors on the job, people who don't
have context who have not been working
on that codebase versus you put code
maintainers on the job, the contractors
can be anywhere from 5 to 18x times
slower. And model performance is cons
consistent closer to contractor times
because it's basically never seen that
codebase before. So this suggests that
um when you're dealing with these models
going and solving these tasks this is
still very valuable but at the same time
it's operating more as not someone who
is an expert in that area or has the
context of that area it's more as a low
context human um who's basically been
asked to solve that problem similar to a
contractor.
So that's summarizing the first um
paper. Um but hopefully that gives you a
flavor of when we are measuring the
progress in AI, one of the axes in
agentic evaluations that becomes
important is to measure how long are the
tasks that uh the AI can complete
reliably.
Any questions or comments before we move
to the next section?
Okay.
Okay. So the next paper that we will
look at is GDP val which is evaluating
the model performance on real world uh
economically valuable tasks. So instead
of asking the question can AI do this
where you have a task that you want to
delegate to AI. Uh here the question is
very much around if we were to give this
task to the model instead of a human is
the output good enough and um the win
rate will be directly against industry
experts. Um so it will actually take the
task suite is designed as real work from
professionals who have more than a
decade of experience in their fields and
so you will see here that the kind of uh
professions that were used for task
suite design are pretty broad ranging
here. So it goes anywhere from say real
estate uh where you take a broad uh so a
broad range of tasks to government to
manufacturing
u professional scientific and technical
services healthcare finance retail
wholesale and information uh including
film and video editors. So it's actually
a pretty broad range of tasks and given
the models have become multimodal this
is does make sense. Um
the models will not be good at all of
these tasks. They will only be good at
some of these tasks of course. So let's
take a look at some example tasks here
and um also think about the tasks that
you think that the models u might be
good at as you uh go through this list.
So in manufacturing engineer it's being
asked to design a 3D model of a cable
reel stand uh for assembly line. In
financial and investment analyst, it's
being asked to uh create the competitive
landscape. So, it's a research heavy
task. In registered nurse, it's
basically assessing the images of a uh
issue and um creating a consultation
report.
Um in film and video editor, it's asking
um to create a intro real given some set
of script. In customer service, it's
being asked to draft an email response
uh for dissatisfi dissatisfied customer.
In concurge, it's basically creating an
itenary for a family of four.
Um in audit uh it's basically figuring
out pricing uh inconsistencies between
given uh a few different purchase
orders. For a real estate agent, it's
designing a sales brochure for a new
property. And in a recreation worker,
it's basically asked to optimize the
layout for a uh a vendor fair.
What do people think? These are very
real tasks from like act actually
sourced from professionals uh in their
fields. Very interesting, right?
Many things is like very subjective to
>> very subjective to
I mean what I feel is going to be what
YouTube
>> yeah so that's why the success metric
here will be win rate right it's not
like if you put humans on the job versus
you put uh models on the job what is the
win rate and and there might be specific
style and that the model chooses that
doesn't quite hold for all cases
yes so it's subjective and at the same
time that subject Objective nature also
makes makes one of the challenges right
that's why real world work requires both
context and subjectivity in how things
get evaluated
what are other real world tasks that
people have seen that are interesting
related to this
you brought up about like you put
private wiki QA and and use that to
query the knowledge base in your in your
job
>> that feeling of coming in That's what
we're finding. It's actually better
finding dead parts of the wiki that are
no longer useful.
>> It's only wiki.
>> Nice.
>> Any other ideas?
>> Other tasks. Yeah. So doctor is not
claiming they has no respect. I feel for
controversial topics if not there
is something
>> or like on the lawyer side whether this
person based on those context are like
commitment
>> so I think lawyers are here uh for
example there are tasks I think uh we
should separate out there's definitely a
question around whether the models are
good at it and whether we want to use
them for ethics and and actual um
compliance reasons. So I think those two
questions need to be separated out from
what models can do today and um so this
is more about is the model output good
enough in the subjective areas I'm
trying to see if uh doctors so there's
registered nurses um there's a lot of
tasks but they put registered nurses and
nurse practitioners in healthcare more
than doctors. Okay. What about the
people who do like for the information s
they don't mention like musician
>> say that again
>> compose a song
>> or birthday song or for someone
>> I see okay
>> so they yes that's correct so maybe
there's an emotion task that will show
up but that's not part of this benchmark
just yet
>> one comment on that maybe for like music
like composing music the verification is
quite subjective or it's harder to say
like I guess you can make sort of like
main music and among them it's hard to
differentiate and I feel like maybe like
what you're trying to like so that they
can kind of there is a deliverable
that's fairly clear if it is working or
not.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. So top down uh this data set this
evaluation data set targets about nine
sectors and they actually went for top
5% of the GDP. So they're asking what
are the most economically valuable tasks
and whether the models are good enough
at that. They cover about 44 occupations
and sourced about 30 20 tasks through
that um and two uh 200 of them or 220 of
them are actually in an open goal set
that is on hiking phase. Uh
predominantly went for um digital tasks.
So tasks on computer uh which is um 60%
of the so Ostar net is a texonomy of all
tasks um that are related to
occupations. So 60% of the OAR net tasks
that are computer- based uh and digital
made it into this evaluation data set
and this basically uh is a pretty
representative coverage of uh various
set of tasks that uh an occupational
expert will need to do in these
particular sectors.
And in terms of uh the characteristics
of tasks that people went after, uh they
might have as long as seven hours of
completion time on average, but some
might require weeks. Um
the tasks were both text based and
multimodal. So like CAD, video, audio,
spreadsheets, presentations. Uh the
average value of the task at least in
the gold subset was anywhere from say
$400 uh per task. Um but if anyone has
se seen swelancer there's also like much
higher value tasks. So this one also has
high value and low value tasks. Many of
these tasks about 70% of these tasks
require interaction with the reference
files. So you have to interact with some
reference files to uh arrive at a final
output. And um the all of these tasks
were vetted through experts. So uh about
89% of the tasks were actually vetted by
experts as being very well specified. So
they were not like ill specified and and
extremely hard for the model just
because they're illsp specified. So if
you look at the trend uh so on the
x-axis now you see different models all
the way from GPD 40 to GPD5 high to cla
uh opus 4.1 and on the y-axis you're
looking at win rate versus um the
industry professional. So basically if
you had an expert with more than a
decade of experience uh solving it
versus uh the model solving it. So light
blue is wins plus ties and dark blue is
wins only. Uh there's a pair-wise
preferences. Uh so if you look at GPD40
on an average the average numbers don't
mean that every single task was solved
like that go anywhere from say 12.4%. So
that's 2024 uh to it starts to get to 25
and then more recently it is in 30s and
then now with claude opus 4.1 it starts
to get to like 47.6. So that's a very
different trend compared to METR where
we were talking about this doubling
trend every seven months. It's more of a
linear uh trend roughly compared to the
exponential trend that METR was talking
about. And at the same time uh this is
real work where you are comparing
relative to an expert. So the
measurement is very much based on
whether this task whether the model
output was good enough or not. So the
reliability or rather the model output
being useful matters here.
questions.
>> Yes.
>> Is this [clears throat]
trend directly comparable to the meter
one though? Because here the by accident
is like win rate versus industry
professional as opposed to you know the
uh time prize and
>> that's in the in the other case. So yeah
should I really think about them and
disagreeing?
I would say that this say green versus
not because they're measuring different
metric as we said earlier on but I think
uh what it's roughly emphasizing is that
uh when you see an exponential trend uh
people often assume that okay so now the
now AI can do one hour so next it will
be able to do couple of hours and the
next it will be able to do couple of
days so there is that exponential trend
that gets people what this is saying is
that if you look at tasks that require
say several hours or a couple of days or
a couple of weeks then the models are
only so reliable in doing that and it's
actually breaking it down by profession.
So it kind of makes it more realistic by
nailing it down not just by numbers of
uh hours but more by this is real work
and can the AI models do it or not
>> other comments? Yeah,
>> I guess like this chart is like on the
aggregate level right across all the
professions.
>> We will look at the specific ones as
well. So there might be maybe ones that
are more susceptible or ignorant. I
guess
>> another set of comments with respect to
uh say the model specific strengths is
that broad always tends to be better I'd
say aesthetics document formatting
understanding PDFs spreadsheets and
presentations while um GBD5 often tends
to be better at say instruction
following correct calculations and just
textbased tasks. So that's something
that was noticed by this particular um
evaluation. [snorts]
And then if you look at failure modes
which is very important to analyze in uh
most of these benchmarks then often
times the common area of failure ends up
being instruction following. So uh a lot
of u a lot of the blue bars show
different instruction following errors
in in different models. Um often times u
the models will promise to look at the
reference data but then actually not
look at it. um they will override it
with whatever hallucination they want to
come up with and then uh there's also
formatting errors that tend to be a bit
of a problem um but GBD5 tends to have
fewer instruction following error is is
what was uh measured by this particular
benchmark [sighs]
uh related to the reference data. So our
next uh particular section of the uh
lecture will actually discuss more about
that like being able to consult a
knowledge base or a reference uh data
and why that's like an important
[snorts] skill to go test.
Okay. And then in terms of more on the
uh failure modes. So this was basically
measuring whether GPD5 um if you look at
the percentage of tasks that will
generally be seen as acceptable but
subpar if you like delegated that task
to the model uh what they found was that
roughly half the tasks were acceptable
but subpowered but then uh only 20% of
the tasks fell somewhere like okay the
model would genuinely be better. Um
and in 20 29% of the tasks were like bad
or catastrophic where the model output
was really not acceptable at all and
there was some amount of uh disagreement
between human graders uh with respect to
whether they agree on um what the
assessment of the model output is or
not. So that also affects some of this
analysis.
Okay. Um and then another interesting
thing is the is something that since
this is a self-improving agents class.
So um a lot of times if you basically do
parallel sampling so if you try
something or sequential sampling where
you do something end times um then ask
the model to fix itself based on
whatever it was seeing that loop can
often uh really improve. So what this
particular table is showing is that you
can either do naive just one trial or
you can do uh so you can try one time or
you can try n times where you basically
uh every single time you do something
you can improve uh the last iteration.
So in terms of speed improvement uh what
they found was that GBD5 was overall uh
about 1.6x in in cost improvement if you
could try end times and about 1.4 in
speed improvement relative to an unaded
expert. But there is still where it's
successful. It is still less than 10% of
the human expert salary. So there's
definitely some subset of professions
where the models are doing a pretty
strong job uh and and are have the
capability to take on that tasks
completely.
>> So so people also imagine exactly which
>> we will get there.
>> Um that's exactly where we're going.
So in terms of performance variation um
so by sectors in government, retail and
wholesale um I think the broad items the
broad categories are not that
illustrative looking at a specific task
help but they are the performance was
near par relative to human experts by
duration. uh the models were better at
shorter tasks up to a few hours u
definitely declines with longer tasks
and uh we already discussed that on
modality there some models were better
at multimodal while others were better
at text okay this is going to be an
extremely dense uh plot but I think the
thing to notice here in all of these
plots is that the red line is the one
where we are saying the human experts uh
are and then all of these different
colors are corresponding to different
models. So if you look at places where
the models are better or at least are
almost at par with the human experts,
you see that counter and rental clerk.
So some of those tasks have already
started to hit that. Real estate brokers
for example, uh shipping, receiving and
in inventory clerks, for example, buyers
and purchasing agents, you can imagine
why. Um computer and IT system managers
are definitely like it's starting to hit
where human an average human expertise
would be. When I say average, this is
not like um the best expert in the
field. And then software developers
definitely u a lot of the models are
starting to hit capability in in typical
software engineering tasks.
I'm seeing some um interesting
reactions from students in in class. Can
I have some comments?
for the software I know that you
mentioned previously is like human is
the 14 years of experience
>> but software you it can be like the the
range can be pretty wide so
>> I I I think in case of software
developers they probably went for more
of the maintainers of the repository as
opposed to like the decade of experience
I think there are fields here where I
mean for example industrial engineer
mechanical engineer the the decade of
experience matters and software
developer knowing the software copies in
in and out and in cases of that that
part as well.
Okay, this is another one of those plots
but let's just focus on uh where uh
we're seeing the models do extremely
well. So again in government the
administrative service managers um in
compliance officers multiple uh models
are doing extremely well. Um and then in
medical and health service managers
those tasks multiple models are doing
extremely well in personal personal
financial advisor and customer service
representatives also you're starting to
see that the models are starting to do
extremely well but in general this give
you gives you a glossery or a taxonomy
of set of tasks that the models are
starting to perform well in. And if
you're looking at other tasks where the
models are failing, I think this is a
very good way to get a starting point on
like what are the models failing at
questions or comments.
Okay, this is the last round I promise.
Um, so first line supervisors and retail
sales workers I think and in general in
retail trading we are starting to see uh
some uh some of those tasks taken on by
the models as useful. Same for non-
retail sales workers. So in general on
the sales side in terms of editing tasks
we are seeing the models do extremely
well. Um in terms of research based
tasks um uh both investigative and
detection based detective based and news
analysts and then sales representatives
um wholesale and manufacturing those
tasks seem to uh suggest that the models
are doing extremely well. Um so these
this gives you a flavor of the kind of
task that the models are are performing
strongly at.
Overall if you underspecify the prompts
so if you actually remove context from
the prompt then the models do end up uh
not doing that well. Um in their
particular case there was a few points
uh lower in terms of win rate but in
terms of actual model output the models
actually struggle to figure out what to
work on. So there's definitely uh some
amount of when you're doing real work
and you can specify all the context that
the human had in their head to go do the
work and it's mostly about reasoning and
they just going and executing a certain
set of tool calls and the models can do
the job but there's a lot of figuring
out what needs to be worked on how that
context needs to be used what needs to
be in the context and a lot of that
doesn't get captured by the model on its
own. So that's definitely one area where
um the humans have to orchestrate what
is it what is the actual thing to go
work on.
So humans are basically architecting
what is the set of problems and then the
model can go solve it in certain cases.
And and this is further exemplified by
what we covered before where if you had
a repository maintainer versus an
external contractor, the speed at which
the repository maintainer is able to
solve problems is generally much faster.
So if you have an expert who has uh
domain knowledge, they will generally be
faster uh compared to someone who has no
context. So real work is often context
heavy and what we are measuring in this
particular evaluation is more around can
a smart person do this or can someone
embedded in this work can do this but if
you have to go get context for that task
that models are not yet able to do and
then this evaluation is not measuring
that
so in near term what this means is that
AI assistance is already happening in
professional workflows we have covered
some of the agentic workflows in early
part of the lecture and is definitely
cost effective when you couple it with
human oversight. Like if the humans are
architecting what the models need to go
work on, the AI assistance is definitely
helping. Um in certain occupations, this
is more um impactful than not. But as uh
but you do have to choose different
models and um different models are
stronger at different task types as
well.
Okay,
questions or comments?
Yes.
>> Um how like much weight should you put
on the actual dollar value?
>> Yeah.
>> Um why do you ask that question?
>> Well, because it seems like uh
like it's a relevant way of uh
quantifying actual economic impact. say,
"Oh, the AI can now do like, you know,
$100,000 of work like that." [snorts]
Uh, but if these numbers are collected
in a way that seems unreliable or
misleading, then
>> uh, you know, what?
>> I think to me it's not so much about the
dollar. I mean they did go after the top
5% of the GP uh tasks uh for the past um
I mean several decades of knowledge work
has been one of the key areas that has
seen the highest grade profession and in
knowledge work there are certain
categories of tasks will be very good at
um deep research being one of them
perhaps um another one being like code
generation so in each of or
understanding a diverse set of
information sources so the models will
generally be good at those set of tasks
so I think the question I would ask is
what is the category uh of task that the
models are likely to be good at just
because at any given point in time
humans are strong at certain set of
things and machines just by way of being
able to uh crunch um with electricity
are just better at certain set of things
right so this is more along those lines
so there are certain category of tasks
that will definitely um
be valuable delegating to the model is
is the way to look at it and and which
are the professions in which those cate
category of task fall is what this
benchmark is is showcasing.
Before this uh benchmark came out,
people would talk about this area of
like okay this is going to impact a lot
of professions but there was no
quantitative way to measure what set of
tasks in each of these professions and
it seemed like a humongous task to go do
that. So this is a very verifiable
quantifiable way to even like have a
texonomy
to list the set of tasks in each of the
professions and what does it mean for
the model to go do them. Um earlier um
when we were doing the class um in the
previous iteration we were only talking
about MLB and rebing given that um our
backgrounds are say more ML or more
research or more uh software it's easier
for us to understand the uh progress of
um these models in those those domains.
I'm just curious how like when the model
perform
it just means
like the human not necessarily those
profession
anymore. I mean this is where I was
adding these caveats right so when a
model is outperformed the human you
should go look at the prompt and what
they're saying is that for a human who
has a lot of context um if they were to
specify all the context in their head to
specify it in a prompt then the models
can also do those tasks right
u while if but a lot of actual work
experience or a lot of workplace uh
challenges often are about figuring out
what to prioritize what are the set of
problems to solve
uh where to put uh resources.
Okay. Uh we will move to the last um
benchmark which will be focused on new
scholar bench. Um this was a task that
one of our classmates requested early on
where they want AI to write the
literature review section of their
paper. So here we are. Let's benchmark
that task. Um this was written at
Stanford and this is basically measuring
the um the question of instead of asking
uh how long will um the task take to
solve um is the model output good enough
they're actually asking can AI perform
deep research synthesis can I go study a
bunch of references and retrieve the
relevant information and then synthesize
the findings into a coherent set of
reports so that and and have verifiable
citations and there have been several um
industry prototypes that have come out.
So there's OpenAI deep research, Gemini
Deep Research, Perplexity uh has a deep
research thing. Storm is from Stanford.
There's Open Scholar. Um you folks built
a deep research agent in homework 3 and
maybe you got a flavor of like what that
feels like. So in general there has been
a lot of research activity in this area
and it still continues to be a
challenging area is what this paper
shows. Um
so the task that this uh paper addresses
is to generate the related work section
for academic papers. Um the reason they
care about this task is because um this
is a task that most of us require when
we are writing papers. Uh and it
requires continuous updates with fresh
queries. So there is not no staleness.
The way they went about constructing
this data set is they uh used recent
archive papers with PhD level difficulty
across 22 domains and um they rerun it
monthly with new papers. So uh it stays
live. So it's it's very nice in that
respect as well and it avoids uh data
contamination. They only look at papers
that are post um training uh of a major
model. So that's very nice. What they're
evaluating the models on is uh three
particular axes. So the first thing
they're evaluating the model on is
knowledge synthesis. So what they're
basically saying is that is the model
output uh organizing and is coherent in
organizing the knowledge that is
presenting and is it capturing all the
key facts. So is it capturing the key
nuggets.
The second axis it's u evaluating the
model on is retrieval quality. So if
it's looking at a particular set of
references, how relevant they are to
what you wanted to do research on. For
example, if you're writing a related
work section for your uh project for for
your final project uh and you have say
10 references that uh this uh model or
agent went and and fetched, are they
relevant to what you actually want to
present in your final report or not? Uh
citation counts. uh it's kind of well
known that you want highly authentic
sources. So whether the papers are
important uh in terms of covering um
those in the retrieval and then
reference coverage u so this is ref
similar to like is it finding important
papers or not um and then the third axis
it uh it's measuring is verifiability.
So um do the citations support the
claims? So even if it finds good papers
and it's citing some aspect of that
paper is the claim uh supported by that
citation and then uh our claims backed
by the citation. So these two are very
similar but one is bas measuring
precision and one is measuring coverage
and each of these metrics are actually
validated um by humans. So they got
about 70 to 80% of human agreement when
they got humans to evaluate this.
Now the fun thing is that most
benchmarks get saturated. So when we
look at benchmarks we're like okay well
it's already at 70% or 80% so there is
no headroom. The fun thing about this
particular benchmark is that none of the
existing systems actually exceeds 19%.
So if this were to show up in your
homework for the next iteration of the
class a lot of headroom for you folks to
actually make it a final project.
[snorts]
um in terms of if you look at u each of
these axes on which they are breaking
down the model performance in terms of
knowledge synthesis they they found that
open aid research does a pretty good job
but almost all of the models
consistently uh miss key facts so even
though they write coherently so it's
great English but not necessarily
covering all the key facts uh the
retrieval quality tends to be u overall
um okayish so all systems um currently
struggle to find comprehensive and
important set of sources. Uh the
document importance um in all of them is
less than 12.5%. And then finally um if
you look at verifiability they found
that
say deep scholar base uh got up to like
90 90% precision but open deep research
has lower verifiability despite the fact
that it does a really good job at
writing um really nice English. So the
uh the synthesis is extremely coherent.
Now if you look at the failure modes and
and that's where a lot of the learnings
lie. Um
typically the failure modes come from
not finding comprehensive sources. So
even when they do find relevant
documents they're not always finding the
foundational papers. So this is where if
you are an expert in the area you kind
of know from experience that there are
all these foundational papers because
they you kind of build that context and
and bookmark all the important papers.
uh the uh deep research agents do a
reasonably strong job but they struggle
to assess the document importance uh
beyond whether that's relevant to the
context or not. Uh they surface
essential facts. So even with good
retrieval they don't always uh extract
the key information efficiently. If you
do give the perfect sources um so even
if you say that okay here are all the
papers that should have been included
even then if you try to get them to
extract the key facts even then they get
about 50% coverage and without knowing
the exact papers they get lower coverage
and then finally if you're trying to
balance out the qual synthesis quality
versus verifiability
none of the systems actually uh excels
at both like the quality of synthesis
and the verifiability in certain ways.
So you can see that uh being able to
refer to reference data in in the
Asianic evaluation tasks is a
non-trivial problem. So it's not just
about how long a task is or whether it's
real world economic value or not. If you
have to reference some reference data to
look go look at it's non-trivial because
you might not get the context that an
expert has. So you might not have that
much foundational knowledge available.
It might not extract the key information
well enough. So it does something but
not uh it so it's good with human AI
assistance and the verifiability with
respect to citations may not have the
right precision recall trade-off that's
acceptable for that occupation.
So what that roughly means so this is
transitioning uh to summarize across all
the papers but before I go there let me
uh open up for questions just on the
deep scholarbench style of tasks.
Any questions or comments?
>> Yeah.
>> Seems like a much more specific narrow
thing than the other two.
>> Yes.
>> Um like why talk about this one in
particular as opposed to any other any
other.
So I think the broad theme of the
lecture was very much focused on um what
what do we care about in agentic
evaluations per se right so we covered
about the length of the tasks we talked
about the economic value of the tasks
but for real world tasks to be
meaningful we do have to look at
knowledge bases in useful ways so this
is a representative task for that
category
>> bottles for like the the most
foundational papers. So like this I
guess like for the benchmark there's a
list that's connected from human experts
right like they like these are the
papers that people like the PhDs think
like the model can hit and then you were
trying to see like how many were
actually like retrieved or whatever like
by the the model being tested is that
>> I mean at any given point in time
they're basically saying um yes so
there's a human aspect of like here are
the list of papers that there but You're
also looking at whether it's I mean
it's not just the number of uh the set
of papers right it's also talking about
are you supporting if you want to make a
set of claims when you write the related
work section you're answering the
question of like how is this work
related so you want to make a set of
claims my paper is different from these
other papers and let's say agree on a
set of topics with the model you still
have to make a bunch of claims and then
you have to look at the citations and
back those claims up and then say that
your paper is different in this
particular regards and then this is what
being covered by the field. So even the
the key information coverage and then
which papers get referenced for those
claims don't have sufficient um coverage
and so on.
So it's both retrieval quality and then
what gets written down in terms of the
key funds.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So let's try to summarize across a
different set of tasks. So um and this
is kind of also addressing the question
that our classmate asked. Um so in the
time horizon sense um research synthesis
tasks uh can be anywhere from 30 minutes
to 8 hours but uh the current capability
range is somewhere around 50 minutes but
the quality at this horizon might still
be poor. You might still end up with say
50% success rates. So uh what this is
roughly saying is that if research
synthesis tasks are in uh long horizon
in MTR and even though they look good on
that plot they might not be um might not
be high quality in terms of economic
value. Um I mean research synthesis
tasks show up in say financial investig
uh financial research. They show up in a
lot of different research tasks, but um
so they have clear economic value, but
they definitely require capabilities um
that current models are not always
hitting. And often times the gaps are
coming from say multi-step reasoning
from being able to do a comprehensive
job at information gathering to maintain
verifiability while you're synthesizing
this information. So if you remember
from homework three when you basically
combine information from multiple
different agent calls you still have to
maintain certain amount of verifiability
and then you are combining the context.
So there's context engineering from a
distributed set of sources. Maybe you
did a bunch of different tool calls. You
maybe you did went and did read red read
redid the tool calls. So all of that
information needs uh you have to
maintain the context in in each of those
multi-step uh scenarios. So we are not
just limited by task duration. How well
we do in terms of quality of synthesis
um at these time horizons also has a lot
of headroom for improvement.
And how does this vary from a real world
task? So I mean as I said before so
benchmarks are never perfect. They are a
representation of what we think is uh
measurable today. And um so METR is uh
automatically scored. Uh there's no
multi- aent interaction. So it's
basically uh targeting a set of tasks
that are sort of um single agent uh and
it's not punishing of mistakes and the
resource constraints there's no resource
constraints in terms of like uh how much
resources can be used. So it's basically
um in real work you might actually have
um more subjective constraints and how
things are scored. You might be able to
break down the task into multiple agents
which might actually lead to a better
evaluation and then there might be
actual resource constraints or cost of
mistakes.
Uh in the second set of paper that we
covered called GDP val which focuses
very much on economically valuable tasks
the the the key aspect there is that the
tasks are extremely well specified like
all the context that the human would
have in their head gets specified in the
task and it's one shot. So there's no
iterative back and forth where you get
to uh fix what the model did. Um and it
requires the model to have some amount
of tacet knowledge. So it needs the
knowledge to be there already in the
model. And that gap gets covered more by
the third benchmark that where we were
looking at research synthesis. Uh here
the challenges are that it's the models
still struggle with like finding
comprehensive highquality sources and uh
surfacing key facts and then verifying
them. And these are things that if a
human is an expert in the field and does
this day in and day out, they'll be much
faster at because they just have that
context in their head all the time.
So what do we know now in terms of model
capabilities and where there's headroom
for improvement? So we kind of know that
the models have been improving on
isolated well specified tasks. If you if
you have a set of tasks that are well
specified and fall in [snorts] uh the
set of domains where the models are good
at, then they do a really good job. uh
software engineering and ML research are
two domains where we have seen
significant progress perhaps because as
computer scientists and computer
engineers we tend to understand those
domains better. So we are automating
away our own jobs. Uh
uh but uh so we definitely are seeing
these models do a a really good job in
terms of say uh solving hourlong tasks
there and um the stronger models can
generate very well organized outputs
even if um not all parts of that outputs
are correct.
What we have lower confidence in if you
look at model capabilities is that um
the models uh perform uh performance on
uh tasks where you need a lot of context
is low. So if you don't have the context
in the model's uh prompt then the model
doesn't quite know what to go work on.
It doesn't quite figure out am uh
ambiguous um prompts and just figure out
what it needs to uh figure out to solve
the problem. um the performance in
adversarial environments are not uh is
not necessarily great. Uh overall if you
want 95% reliability the models are not
quite there and generally we have not
yet seen a lot of generalization beyond
software and knowledge work where
knowledge work encompasses a lot of the
digital work workloads today. Um
we also think that the models um are
still not strong at uh finding
comprehensive high-quality sources when
they have to reference uh knowledge
bases and uh surface key facts and then
verify what they surfaced as high
accuracy and high coverage in the
knowledge base. So all of these um are
still gap areas and model capabilities.
So if we were to uh summarize across the
three uh papers that we uh talked about
today in METR we talked about uh the
seven-month doubling horizon in terms of
model capabilities um as in the models
can complete the tasks um with 50%
reliability. uh that time horizon has
been doubling every 7 months and the
forecast is that say 2028 to 2031 it
will almost be a one month task can be
completed by the model u but that view
gets uh contradicted in some ways by GDP
val win rate which shows more of a
linear improvement over the last two
years um where even though the win rate
for certain set of tasks is 48% at the
same time um you will see that there are
many category of tasks that don't high
win rates and then the other gap area
that you see is that a lot of the tasks
in GDB val actually require context or
require looking at reference data and
deep scholar bench uh the research
synthesis task kind of shows you that
there's critical gaps when you have to
go retrieve some set of context or look
at a knowledge base and generally the
quality and the verifiability don't
quite um match up u compared to what a
human would be able to do.
So in general uh the reliability and the
error recovery of the models should
continue to improve but the performance
will vary still over task uh types like
which category of tasks we are looking
at. Uh so even if the models are solving
longer and longer horizon tasks that
doesn't necessarily mean they're always
giving highly reliable or quality
outputs. So we need uh metrics which are
duration based, economic value based and
also synthesis quality based and and you
still need to validate them against
humans who can solve these tasks.
Okay, with that I will actually open up
for questions.
Go back to the question I asked what
does the team so what do you think about
the developility like for
show
>> similar to like
more slow so I'm just curious because
you are not experts and like what do you
think
>> so I think there was two answers to your
question I mean swing bench definitely
show swing bench verify for example has
shown a really strong role in general in
coding area. Um we will continue
continue to see improvements and still
there's a large category of tasks uh
which are um not just p request based
and so on and these are hard tasks. So
um there's a longtail task that will
continue to be challenging for the
models. I mean the first 80% was hard to
do easy to do and then last 20% took a
decade.
distributed systems being one of the
areas in which computer science where
it's very hard for the models to get it
right.
You mentioned a couple times like uh on
what your sense
of like what um how you expect your own
brand to look different like 2 years
from now.
>> Um
so I I think timelines are moving
extremely fast uh in ways where u it's
very hard to predict something one year
from now. I think one of my task would
end up being self equal to what an AI
scientist does. An AI scientist being
able to come up with hypothesis and run
the experiments and then like complete
the whole loop is um still something of
that that that is our definition of AGI
is to like when AI can build the next
generation of models themselves then we
don't have to even be in the room. Uh
but I I don't think that is quite there
yet. uh that it's definitely been
fascinating to see the level of progress
in terms of how the AI models do have
the knowledge base and often are
extremely strong uh brainstorming uh
partners. So it's AI co-scientist at
this point in time um which has a better
um better value for for a lot of the use
cases uh is is how I see it.
I also generally feel that in most areas
um getting reliability uh or the long
tail of reliability is going to be
extremely challenging. Um so so that's
that's the area in which the the fine
the last one was is hard to get
progress.
>> I thought more of a clarification
question about the meter paper. Um so
they they talk about this concept of
like 50% task completion rate. Um I was
wondering like if the 50% is like an
average kind of like success rate maybe
let's say so there let's say that there
are like 100 test instances right um and
then for each test instance like the AI
will try 10 times and then you see you
count you know how many times then it
fails or it succeeds
>> and then you kind of take the average
over you know the 10 the 100 times 10 or
is it sort of more like you want to be
like make sure for every task it has at
least like 50% cuz I feel like the will
be much more stringent right and harder
to achieve.
>> I think it's multiple attempts for sure
because if you remember we showed this
bot right so there are multiple agent
runs and it's basically saying how how
many times it completed successfully.
So like you have like maybe like so yeah
so here let's say like there are like 97
tasks. So each task you will calculate
like a success rate right of the agent
and then you will take the average of
the individual like task success rate
across the 97 is that like kind of what
do you think they're doing to get the
final 50%.
So uh yes roughly right like for each
horizon they're basically drawing these
points and the points are the the the
success rate for each task is coming
from what percentage of uh attempts were
successful.
So 50% success rate for a particular
task roughly would mean that 50% of the
time it might come back with a good
answer 30% maybe not. So it's of
those results like so it's doing much
better
self engineer learning time was
otherwise experience.
>> Okay let's take that off for the class.
>> Okay. Yeah. Um I think the computer
science as a profession is not going
anywhere. Um and if you're able to
reason for fundamentals, um that is very
important skill to have. Um AI as you
saw needs needs to figure out the
context to solve anything. So you need
to be able to give it the context.
So that that's my belief.
>> Okay.
>> All right. I I have a question. What's
what do you think are stopping AI from
uh tackling those long tail
problem? There's a lack of data or what
else? I mean what's the fundamental
implications?
This
>> um I mean it's it's a mix of both a data
problem and a fundamental model
capabilities, right? in certain cases uh
if you
I think there are several startups that
are tackling things um and building
environments and whatnot but coming up
with tasks that are uh representative
and then uh stop gapping the model
capabilities in each of these tasks
continues to be an area which is
challenging at this point in time right
so um I think when they are brought
across categories like say legal
research or financial research those
have seen much faster adoption and and
improvement ments but they're when
they're very very specific like and
having enough data to or having the
right model having the model progress
and the right model capabilities is hard
for example if you look at robotics
other domain right which is um the
embodied AI stuff there's like a whole
suite of startups that are just going
after data collection as the primary
hypothesis to close the gap based on top
of these models
okay
thank